Guide to the Helen Miller Gould Shepard Papers 1814-1941 MS 1422
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
The Helen Miller Gould Shepard Papers
1814-1940
MS 1422
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
4.5 Linear feet (11 boxes, 1 volume, 1 oversize folder)
Helen Miller Gould Shepard (1868-1938) was the eldest daughter of railroad financier Jay Gould, and a prominent philanthropist. This collection contains correspondence, ephemera, scrapbooks, published materials, visual material, and writings by Helen Miller Gould. The bulk of the collection is ephemera regarding her social, philanthropic, and religious occupations.
Shepard, Helen Miller Gould, 1868-1938
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Scope and Content Note
The Helen Miller Gould Shepard Papers contains correspondence, ephemera, scrapbooks, published materials, and writings, and visual material created by or relating to the life of Helen Miller Gould. The bulk of the collection is ephemera relating to her social, philanthropic, and religious occupations, as well as genealogical research. The bulk of the ephemera is comprised of certificates, invitations, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and programs regarding membership in a number of ancestral, religious, family and other organizations as well as programs commemorating her philanthropic work. The collection contains a series of religious tracts written and published by Helen Miller Gould entitled “Passages to Memorize: Suggested by Helen Gould Shepard.”
Correspondence includes both letters to family as well as letters concerning her abundant charitable works such as Woody Crest, a fresh air charity and home for physically handicapped children; her benevolence to soldiers during the Spanish-American War; and the Lyndhurst Sewing School for local young ladies. Frequent correspondents include family members, Mrs. Russell Sage, and many well-known people of the day. Her earlier correspondence to Mrs. Russell Sage and family members is more intimate in nature than later correspondence, which is more formal, mostly relating to her philanthropic and religious work.
A significant portion of this material documents her philanthropic and volunteer efforts on behalf of the United States government, American soldiers, and the Young Men’s Christian Association. A significant portion of the collection documents her donation to the United States government at the outset of the Spanish-American war in 1898 and Congressional commendation given in her honor in 1899. Notable in the collection is a bound scrapbook given to Helen Miller Gould Shepard by Congressman Joseph Wheeler, the Representative from Alabama who nominated her for commendation. A smaller portion of the collection contains some correspondence and documents created by her father, notable financier Jay Gould and a larger portion of correspondence, ephemera, and published material pertaining to Jay Gould.
Arrangement Note
The Helen Miller Gould papers are arranged into the following series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Writings by Helen Miller Gould Shepard
Series III: Ephemera
Series IV: Scrapbooks
Series VI: Published Material
Series VII: Visual Material
Historical Note
Helen Miller Gould Shepard, the eldest daughter of famed New York financier Jay Gould (1836-1892) and Helen Day Miller (1838-1889), was born in Manhattan, New York on June 20, 1868. Helen spent much of her childhood between Manhattan and Lyndhurst, their summer estate in Tarrytown, New York. Helen inherited the Lyndhurst estate after her father’s death in 1892. Helen married Finley Johnson Shepard (1867-1942), a “railroad man”, on January 22, 1913 at the age of 45. The couple adopted three children, Finley Jay, Olivia, and Helen Anna.
Helen’s adult life was marked by her dedication to philanthropy, patriotism, and religious endeavors. Helen began her most notable philanthropic activities in the last decade of the 19th century. Helen opened the Lyndhurst estate to the community and hosted ill and impoverished children and families, entertained and tended to injured soldiers during the Spanish-American war, and established a sewing school for young ladies in Lyndhurst. Helen also maintained Woody Crest, a fresh air charity and home for physically handicapped children in Tarrytown, New York.
On May 6, 1898, at the outset of the Spanish-American War, Helen donated $100,000 to the federal government of the United States of America. This sizable personal donation, in addition to her other donations on behalf of war relief, thrust Helen into the national spotlight. In December of the same year Senator Joseph Wheeler of Alabama introduced a bill to the House of Representatives to praise her donation, which was passed in February of 1899. Helen also spent a great deal of time and money supporting the Young Men’s Christian Association. In March and April of 1912, Helen went on a highly publicized coast to coast speaking and fundraising tour on behalf of the Y.M.C.A.
Helen was heavily involved with New York University, having graduated from the NYU Law School for Women in April 1895. Following in her father’s footsteps, Helen donated generously to the University, most notably donating money for the Gould Memorial Library in New York University’s Bronx campus in 1899, which later housed the Hall of Fame of Great Americans established in 1901.
In addition to her charitable contributions, Helen was wholly dedicated to spreading the Christian faith. She was a member of both the American Tract Society and the American Bible Society. In 1918, Helen and Emma Baker Kennedy became the first female vice presidents of the American Bible Society. Helen printed a series of biblical tracts, booklets and leaflets from 1904 until her death. Most notably, her series of tracts entitled “Passages to Memorize: Suggested by Helen Gould Shepard” were published and translated into over twenty languages, including Arabic, Chinese, French, German, and Russian.
Helen Miller Gould Shepard died of a stroke in her Lyndhurst home in Tarrytown, New York on December 21, 1938 at the age of 70.
Separated Materials Note
A scrapbook of newspaper clippings pertaining to the death of Jay Gould, and of information on other Gould family members has been separated from the collection, but remains within the New-York Historical Society. (F128 HC102.5.G68 S5 1892)
Related Archival Materials Note
The New-York Historical Society has "Jay Gould and the Erie Railway: manuscript, 1893", written by G. P. Morosini. This work was dedicated to Helen Miller Gould to assist in her collection of reminiscences about her father (BV Gould, Jay, patrons must use microfilm). The New-York Historical Society also holds an address book kept by Jay Gould (BV Gould, Jay, patrons must use microfilm)
The Administrative Papers of the Chancellor Henry Mitchell MacCracken 1884-1910 held at New York University Archives contains extensive correspondence with Helen Miller Gould concerning scholarships, contributions, and construction at University Heights.
Provenance
Presented to the New-York Historical Society by the Estates of Helen M. Gould Shepard and Finley Johnson Shepard on November 6, 1942.
American Tract Society.; Atlanta (Yacht).; Gould family; Gould, Jay, 1836-1892; Jaudon, Lucy B.; Lyndhurst Sewing School (Tarrytown, N.Y.).; New York University Hall of Fame for Great Americans.; New York University.; Sage, Margaret Olivia Slocum, 1828-1918; Shepard, Helen Miller Gould, 1868-1938; Wheeler, Joseph, 1836-1906; Women's National War Relief Association.; Woody Crest (Organization).; Young Men's Christian Association.; Cabinet photographs; Certificates; Charities--New York (State)--New York; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Diaries; Donations; Ephemera; Fresh-air charity--United States; Humanities -- Study and teaching.; Invitations; Lyndhurst (Tarrytown, N.Y.); Memorials (Commemorative) -- 20th century; Menus; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Newsletters; Newspapers; Notebooks; Pamphlets; Philanthropists; Photographs; Programs (documents); Reminiscences; Roxbury (N.Y.); Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- War work; Tarrytown (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Visiting Cards; Women philanthropists--New York (State); Women's Charities--New York (State)--New York
- Series I: Correspondence, 1836-1936, undated (Box 1, Box 2)
  Arrangement note
  Series I: Correspondence is arranged chronologically by type of correspondence, including general, family, correspondence from a specific person, and correspondence on a single subject.
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Correspondence contains a wide array of correspondents and recipients. General correspondence contains a wide range of subjects, though Margaret Sage stands out as a frequent author and recipient. Family correspondence contains letters to and from Gould family members, particularly her brother Frank Gould. Correspondence regarding Jay Gould mainly contains reminiscences of Jay Gould from friends and relations in response to Helen's efforts to gather information about her father. Correspondence regarding Joseph Wheeler contains letters from the congressman regarding Helen's Congressional recommendation. Correspondence regarding the Y.M.C.A. and soldiers contain both official letters from administrators in the Y.M.C.A. organizations as well as personal letters from individual soldiers. Finally, correspondence regarding the donation of artwork contains a series of letters to and from Helen regarding her personal donation of artwork to various institutions.
  In general, the earliest correspondence contains more intimate letters sent to and from Helen and her parents and friends, particularly Margaret Sage. Later correspondence is more formal, mostly relating Helen Miller Gould Shepard's philanthropic and religious work.
  - General Correspondence, 1836-1896 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1897-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1901-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1921-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family correspondence, 1883-1893 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family correspondence, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence, 1900-1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Jay Gould, 1852-1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence regarding Jay Gould, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Congressman Joseph Wheeler, 1898-1901 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Y.M.C.A., Soldiers, 1898-1922 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence regarding donation of artwork, 1891-1903, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Writings by Helen Miller Gould Shepard, 1880-1938, undated (Box 3, Box 2, Box 11, Box 9)
  Arrangement Note
  Series II: Writings by Helen Miller Gould Shepard is arranged by type and then chronologically.
  Series II: Writings by Helen Miller Gould Shepard contains both personal and published documents created by Helen Miller Gould Shepard including sketchbooks, school composition notebooks, a travel diary, and copies of religious tracts published by Helen. Sketchbooks include both tracings and original sketches by Helen as a young girl. The six notebooks in the series are Helen's school notebooks from Miss Jaudon's School in New York City on various humanities subjects, some of which are written in French. The travel diary chronicles her trip to Europe and Egypt, traveling on the Gould yacht "Atlanta" (Oct. 1877-Feb. 1888).
  - Sketchbooks, 1880-1883 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbooks, 1884, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Passages to Memorize" leaflets, 1904-1938, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Talks by H.G. Shepard" booklets, 1928-1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript, "Ancestral Chart", Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Passages to Memorize", Braille, Undated (Box 9)
  - School notebooks, 1881-1886, undated (Box 11)
  - Travel diary, 1887-1888 (Box 11)
- Series III: Ephemera, 1852-1941, undated (Oversize 12, Box 7, Box 3, Box 6, Box 10, Box 5, Box 8, Box 4)
  Series III: Ephemera is arranged by type and then chronologically.
  Series III: Ephemera makes up the largest series in this collection. Most items in this series pertain to Helen Miller Gould Shepard's philanthropic activities, including her work for war relief, religious groups, and for institutions such as New York University. A large portion of this series is comprised of certificates of membership and of gratitude for charitable works.
  - Banner, Y.M.C.A., 1913 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Certificates, includes photostats, 1892-1913 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Certificates, 1914-1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Certificates (list), Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bound Certificates, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bound Certificates, 1903, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bound Certificates, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bound Certificates, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bound Certificates, 1938, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Congressional Record (copies), 1898-1899 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Invitations from Helen Miller Gould Shepard, 1895-1935, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Invitations to Helen Miller Gould Shepard, 1884-1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Memorials, 1903-1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Memorials for Jay Gould, 1892-1895 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Menus, 1891, 1931, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Helen Miller Gould Shepard, 1890-1941, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Helen Miller Gould Shepard's wedding, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Jay Gould, 1877-1939, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Gould family, 1895-1939, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Miscellaneous, 1879-1940, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlets, 1852-1901 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlets, 1902-1915 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlets, 1920-1936 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1939-1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlets, Women's National War Relief Association, 1897-1899 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Personal items including locks of Helen Miller Gould's hair, bookplates, fabric sample of "coming out" gown, etc., 1870-1882, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1903-1924 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1928-1940, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Speech Transcript, Lieutenant A.W. Kliefoth, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Personal items including engraving plates, ribbons, pins, medals, plaque, metal frame, etc., 1902-1913, undated (Box 8)
  - Certificates, 1894-1930, undated (Box 10)
  - Oversize certificates (not foldered), 1892-1910, undated (Oversize 12)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks, 1898-1925 (Volume 13, Box 7, Box 9)
  Series IV: Scrapbooks contains two bound and three unbound scrapbooks. Except for the scrapbook containing translated copies of "Passages to Memorize" leaflets, the remaining three scrapbooks are comprised of newspaper clippings regarding a specific topic or event and are arranged chronologically. Notable in this series in a bound volume which was given as a gift from Congressman Joseph Wheeler and contains clippings regarding Helen Miller Gould Shepard's Congressional commendation following her $100,000 donation to the federal government of the United States.
  - Scrapbook, Brigham H. Roberts, 1898-1899 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, Helen Miller Gould Shepard country tour, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, "Passages to Memorize", 1922-1925 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, Congressional recognition of Helen Miller Gould Shepard, 1898 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook, Joseph Wheeler, 1898 (Volume 13)
- Series V: Published Material, 1894-1928, undated (Box 7, Box 9)
  Series V: Published Material contains published materials not created by Helen Miller Gould Shepard. Notable in this series are copies of the Woody Crest Monthly leaflets, published by the children and caretakers at Helen Miller Shepard Gould's home for physically handicapped children.
  - Serial, Woody Crest Monthly, 1894-1902 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Scope and Content
    The New York City 100 licensed several products to generate revenue. This series contains materials relating to scarves created by Nicole Miller and dolls marketed by the Home Shopping Network. Items include correspondence, design elements, photographs and documentation of the request for trademark extension (Box 10, Folder 4).
  - Bible, Undated (Box 9)
  - Founders of Church and State, 1928 (Box 9)
  - The Journal of American History, 1908 (Box 9)
  - Memoir of Jay Gould: Extract from "The Railroad in Education", 1896 (Box 9)
- Series VI: Visual Material, 1814-1935, undated (Box 7)
  Series VI: Visual Material contains photographs, photographic negatives, and photostat copies of church documents and certificates of Helen Miller Gould Shepard's wedding. Two photographs depict Jay Gould as a young man and in adulthood and one depicts Helen's mother, Helen Day Miller. The negatives show Helen Miller Gould with unidentified family members.
  - Photographs, 1814-1935, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Negatives, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 8)